Finding aid for the J. Paul Getty Art and Real Estate Holding Companies Records, 1939, 1960-1982 and undated IA20011
Institutional Records and Archives
Art and real estate holding companies records
1939-1982,
undated
(bulk 1960-1982)
Institutional Records and Archives
Getty, J. Paul (Jean Paul), 1892-1976
Gaiola Corporation
Garrett, Stephen
Art Properties, Inc.
Bramlett, Norris (Cagle Norris)
Fine Arts Corporation (J. Paul Getty)
IA20011
12.3 Linear Feet (24 boxes, 1 flat file)
Records include correspondence, memoranda, letters, agenda, minutes, reports, financial documents, legal documents, photographs, and maps related to J. Paul Getty and his art and real estate holding companies (Art Properties, Inc.; Fine Arts Corporation; Gaiola Corporation), 1939, 1960-1982 and undated. The records provide a detailed legal and financial view of the activities of these holding companies during the last decades of Getty's life and the years immediately after his death.
Related Archival Materials Note
The following materials are offered as possible sources of further information on the people, programs, and subjects covered by the records. The listing is not exhaustive.
Getty Institutional Archives
J. Paul Getty Family Papers, circa 1880s-1989 and undated. Institutional Records and Archives, Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA20009.
Financial records, 1953-1981, J. Paul Getty Museum. Institutional Records and Archives, Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA20022.
J. Paul Getty Diaries, 1938-1946, 1948-1976. Institutional Records and Archives, Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA40009.
Acquisition Information
The records in this collection originated in accessions: 1986.IA.11; 1986.IA.12; 1986.IA.13; 1986.IA.38; and 2009.IA.45.
Restrictions on Access
The records in accession 1986.IA.11 are closed to all except the department that created them, the General Counsel, the director of the originating program or division, or their designees until 2012.
The records in accession 1986.IA.12 are closed to all except the department that created them, the General Counsel, the director of the originating program or division, or their designees until 2017.
The records in accession 1986.IA.13, 1986.IA.38 and 2009.IA.45, subject to review for permanently closed information, are open to qualified researchers. Requests for access will be reviewed on a case-by-case basis.
The following types of records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
Records consist of agenda, minutes, memoranda, correspondence, ledgers, reports, legal documents, contracts, inventories, invoices, bills of sale, tax returns, financial documents, check receipts and cancelled checks, stock certificates, bank statements, inventories, maps, and photographs concerning J. Paul Getty and his art and real estate holding companies (Art Properties, Inc.; Fine Arts Corporation; Gaiola Corporation), 1939, 1960-1982 and undated. The records provide a complete legal and financial view of the activities of these holding companies during the last two decades of Getty's life and the years immediately after his death.
Art Properties, Inc. was formed in the United States in 1960 in an effort to establish legal ownership of Getty's art collection by an entity outside of England. Art Properties was liquidated in 1971 and its assets were used to create two new companies, Fine Arts Corporation (to control art objects) and Gaiola Corporation (to control the Italian real estate Getty began purchasing in 1966). Why Art Properties was liquidated is not made clear by the records, and the exact relationship between Fine Arts Corporation and Gaiola Corporation is also not explained in the records; although some of Getty's collection was housed in the Italian properties, they were legally owned by Fine Arts Corporation.
The records of Art Properties Inc. document meetings of the stockholders, and the incorporation and dissolution of Art Properties, Inc.; inventories and valuations of Art Properties' holdings during the 1960s and 1970s; and information about financial activities and tax reporting.
The records of Fine Arts Corporation document shareholder meetings and the liquidation of the corporation. The art object records describe the removal of objects from Sutton Place (Getty's English estate) and La Posta Vecchia (one of Getty's Italian properties) either for transfer to the J. Paul Getty Museum or for sale. The financial records consist of tax returns, documents concerning stock and bank accounts, and correspondence. The insurance records describe coverage for the assets (art objects) of the corporation.
The Gaiola Corporation records describe the purchase and sale of the Italian properties, their condition, and the day-to-day legal, administrative and financial activities of the corporation.
Organization
These records are organized in three series: Series I. Art Properties, Inc., 1939, 1960-1977, undated; Series II. Fine Arts Corporation, 1969-1982; Series III. Gaiola Corporation and Italian properties, 1966-1980, undated.
Biography
American oil tycoon and art collector Jean Paul Getty was born in Minneapolis, Minnesota on December 15, 1892 to George Franklin Getty (1855-1930) and Sarah Catherine McPherson Risher Getty. Around 1906 the Getty family moved to Los Angeles. Jean Paul, called "Paul," attended a private military school before going on to the University of Southern California in Los Angeles and the University of California, Berkeley. In 1911, Paul went to Oxford to study economics and political science, completing his diploma in 1913. Afterwards he embarked on a year-long Grand Tour of Europe, which no doubt sparked his interest in art and antiquities.
In 1914 Paul joined the family oil business and spent a year in the oil fields of Oklahoma. An astute investment in 160 acres near Stone Bluff, Oklahoma led to Paul's announcement two years later that he had earned his first million dollars. He returned to Los Angeles and took a break of more than a year before returning to the oil business. Paul then persuaded his father to shift the focus of the family business to the Los Angeles basin. Paul continued to work for the family company in addition to conducting oil drilling of his own, securing the family fortune by the time the stock market crashed in 1929. Upon his death in 1930 George left controlling interest in the company to Sarah. In 1934 Paul forced Sarah out of control of the company and gave her an annuity. His fortune grew as he acquired the controlling interest in several companies and became the head of a vast organization with activities in oil exploration, transportation, production and marketing, as well as minerals, manufacturing, real estate and agriculture. In the mid-1940s Getty bought the Saudi Arabian portion of the lease on the mineral rights in the Neutral Zone between Saudi Arabia and Kuwait; his wealth dramatically increased when this site produced oil in 1953.
Beginning in the early 1930s Getty lived in a house he built next to William Randolph Hearst's on the beach in Santa Monica. During World War II he moved to Tulsa, Oklahoma for four years to supervise wartime production of parts for Allied aircraft at his Spartan Aircraft plant. In 1946 he purchased 64 acres in Malibu, California and renovated the existing hacienda, known as the Ranch House, where he lived until 1951. When Getty departed the United States for Europe in 1951, he kept his Malibu estate for the display of his art collection and for the possibility of his eventual return. Getty had been collecting art since the 1930s. In 1938 he made his first major purchases: a group of furniture; a carpet that had belonged to Louis XIV, often called "Ardabil Carpet"; and Rembrandt's Marten Looten (he donated the Ardabil Carpet and the Rembrandt to the Los Angeles County Museum of Art in 1954). His other interest was antiquities, fueled by visits to the Vatican Museums that began in 1939. He took pride in being knowledgeable in the areas in which he was collecting and in finding bargains. Getty continued to collect art throughout his lifetime, despite occasional assertions that he was no longer in the market. By 1968 his art collection had begun to outgrow the Ranch House and he began planning a new building on the property to properly house these works. He chose to pattern this new museum building after a first-century Roman country house, based primarily on the plans of the ancient Villa dei Papiri near Herculaneum. This museum, often called the Villa, opened to the public on January 16, 1974.
After leaving the United States Getty lived in hotel suites in Europe until 1960 when he moved to Sutton Place, a historic 72-room Tudor manor located 25 miles southwest of London. In 1957 Fortune magazine designated Getty as the world's wealthiest man, and he became the object of considerable public interest. For the rest of his life, both the respectable press and the tabloids reported on his perceived eccentricities and his private life, which included five marriages and divorces. J. Paul Getty died in England on June 6, 1976 without ever returning to California or seeing his own museum. Much to everyone's surprise Getty left the bulk of his fortune to the museum with a mission to promote "the diffusion of artistic and general knowledge."
J. Paul Getty's publications include:
Getty, J. Paul. The history of the oil business of George F. and J. Paul Getty from 1903 to 1939. Los Angeles (?), 1941.
Getty, J. Paul. Europe in the eighteenth century. [Santa Monica, Calif.]: privately printed, 1949.
Le Vane, Ethel, and J. Paul Getty. Collector's choice: the chronicle of an artistic odyssey through Europe. London: W.H. Allen, 1955.
Getty, J. Paul. My life and fortunes. New York: Duell, Sloan & Pearce, 1963.
Getty, J. Paul. The joys of collecting. New York: Hawthorn Books, 1965.
Getty, J. Paul. How to be rich. Chicago: Playboy Press, 1965.
Getty, J. Paul. The golden age. New York: Trident Press, 1968.
Getty, J. Paul. How to be a successful executive. Chicago: Playboy Press, 1971.
Getty, J. Paul. As I see it: the autobiography of J. Paul Getty. Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall, 1976.
Articles of incorporation; Minutes; Vital records (document genre); Reports; Stock books; Letters (correspondence); Seals (artifacts); Ledgers (account books); Memorandums; Real property -- Italy; Financial records; Art objects -- Collectors and collecting; Legal documents; Check stubs; Agendas (administrative records); Correspondence; Invoices; Photographs; Bylaws; Getty, J. Paul (Jean Paul), 1892-1976
- Art Properties, Inc., 1939; 1960-1977,; undated; Series I.; 3.3 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
  Organization
  These records are organized into three subseries: Subseries I.A. Minutes, agenda and legal records, 1960-1971, undated; Subseries I.B. Art object records, 1939, 1960-1971; Subseries I.C. Financial records, 1960-1977, undated. Subseries I.D. Vital records and seals, 1960-1971, undated.
  Scope and Contents note
  Records consist of agenda, minutes, memoranda, correspondence, legal documents, inventories, invoices, ledger sheets, bills of sale, tax returns, financial documents, check receipts and cancelled checks, and bank statements, of Art Properties, Inc., 1939, 1960-1977, and undated. The records document meetings of the stockholders, specifically activities surrounding the purchase and transfer of works of art, and the incorporation and dissolution of Art Properties, Inc.; inventories of Art Properties' holdings during the 1960s and 1970s, valuations and appraisals of the holdings, and information about the shipping of works of art; and information about purchasing and other financial activities, financial and tax reporting, and the issuance of stock. Subseries I.D., Vital records and seals, contains the company's official embossing seal and vital records, which are original, signed versions of some of the duplicate documents found in subseries I.A., I.B., and I.C.
  Historical Note
  Art Properties, Inc. was "originally formed as the depository for [J. Paul Getty's] personal art collection" and was later liquidated into Fine Arts Corporation and Gaiola Corporation (circa 1970). These companies were dissolved within several years after Getty's death in 1976.
  Getty was the sole stockholder in Art Properties; "ownership of the stock would follow his domicile and through the corporate device hopefully keep the art collection technically out of England and Italy. Fine Arts Corporation was formed to divide it up under different corporate entities for the reasons indicated in the Art Properties minutes, thereby giving flexibility to Mr. Getty." (Personal letter to Joseph Peeler and Norris Bramlett from C. Lansing Hays, dated July 27, 1971.)
  "[The] parent company, Art Properties, Inc., distributed to Mr. Getty, its sole stockholder, all of the stock of the newly formed subsidiaries. It retained art objects which Mr. Getty wanted the Museum to own." (Certificate of Incorporation.)
  Art Properties was liquidated in 1971 into Fine Arts Corporation (art) and Gaiola (Italian real estate).
  - Minutes, agenda, and legal records, 1960-1971; Subseries I.A.; 0.4 Linear Feet (1 box)
    Arrangement
    These records are arranged in general chronological order.
    Records consist of agenda, minutes, correspondence, memoranda, legal documents (certificates of incorporation, reduction and amendment), inventories, invoices, and ledger sheets, of Art Properties Inc., J. Paul Getty's first art holding company, 1960-1971 and undated. The minutes detail the activities of the Board, including election of officers, approval of bills of sale, transfer of art objects to Italy, selection of auditors, and discussions of insurance and financial statements; and the incorporation and dissolution of Art Properties, Inc., in 1960 and 1970, respectively. Original signed versions of some of these documents can be found in Subseries I.D. Vital records and seals.
    - Art Properties Inc. agendas, 1967 (Box 1986.IA.11-01, Folder 1)
    - Art Properties Inc. stockholders meeting minutes and related documents, 1960-1970; [6 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-01, Folder 2-7)
    - Corporate data, 1967-1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-01, Folder 8)
    - Power of attorney, 1967 (Box 1986.IA.11-01, Folder 9)
    - Dissolution data, 1971 (Box 1986.IA.11-01, Folder 10)
    - Art Properties Inc. liquidation, 1969-1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-01, Folder 11)
    - Reorganization [Art Properties Inc.–Fine Arts Corporation–Gaiola], 1968-1970; undated; [3 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-01, Folder 12-14)
    - Liquidization and reorganization, 1970-1971; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-01, Folder 15-16)
  - Art object records, 1939-1971; Subseries I.B.; 0.9 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
    These records are arranged in general subject order.
    Records consist of correspondence, letters, memoranda, invoices, bills of sale, inventories, and ledgers, documenting the holdings and activities of Art Properties, Inc., J. Paul Getty's first art holding company, 1939, 1961-1970. Included in the records is correspondence with a few art dealers regarding the offering and purchase of works of art; inventories and valuations of holdings at Sutton Place and in Italy, some with dispositions (e.g., transferred to Fine Arts Corporation); information about the shipping of purchased art objects to England and Italy; and bills of sale for newly purchased art objects and art objects transferred to Art Properties by Getty. The records also contain a ledger listing all Getty's art objects held at Sutton Place, in addition to photocopies of the ledger, created at an unknown time. Original signed versions of some of the documents in this subseries can be found in Subseries I.D. Vital records and seals.
    See also Subseries I.C. Financial records.
    For more information on the 1970 appraisal conducted by Christie's, see also Series II.A., Appraisal records, Financial records, 1953-1981, J. Paul Getty Museum. Institutional Archives, Research Library, Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA20022.
    - Agnew and Sons Ltd., 1961-1968 (Box 1986.IA.11-01, Folder 17)
    - Wildenstein, 1967 (Box 1986.IA.11-01, Folder 18)
    - Duveen Bros. Inc., 1961 (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 1)
    - Major More-Molyneaux, 1961; 1971 (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 2)
    - Art valuation, 1966-1967 (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 3)
    - "Appraisal of Art Objects" by Spencer Samuels and Company, Ltd., 1967; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 4-5)
    - A.J. Thurgood, 1964-1966 (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence and inventory, Sutton Place, 1964-1967; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 7-8)
    - Sutton Place inventory, 1966 (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 9)
    - Art Properties Inc. art objects (UK and Italy) as of 12/31/69, 1939-1970; [4 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 10-13)
    - Art Properties Inc. inventory, Christie's, May 1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 14)
    - Ledger, 1960-1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-06)
    - Copies of ledger, 1960-1970:
      - Ledger: prints and engravings, statuary and ceramics, room trimmings, miscellaneous, 1960-1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 15)
      - Ledger: tapestries, rugs, sofas and chairs, 1960-1967; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 16)
      - Ledger: tables and cabinets, 1960-1970; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 18-19)
      - Ledger: silver table, glass and china, oil paintings, 1960-1970; [1 of 2] (Box 1986.IA.11-02, Folder 20)
      - Ledger: silver table, glass and china, oil paintings, 1960-1970; [2 of 2] (Box 1986.IA.11-03, Folder 1)
    - Art objects shipped to England and Rome and items returned, 1960-1969; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-03, Folder 2-3)
    - Art Properties Inc. bills of sale and related correspondence and documents, 1960-1970; [4 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-03, Folder 4-7)
  - Financial records, 1960-1977; Subseries I.C.; 1 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
    Records consist of correspondence, memoranda, invoices, tax returns, financial documents, check receipts and cancelled checks, and bank statements of Art Properties Inc., 1960-1977 and undated. The records describe the financial transactions of Art Properties, including the purchase and sale of art objects, the payment of taxes, the issuance of stock, and payments for services rendered. Original signed versions of some of these documents can be found in Subseries I.D. Vital records and seals.
    See also Subseries I.B. Art object records.
    - Correspondence, ledgers re: foreign investments changes and regulations, 1965-1968 (Box 1986.IA.11-03, Folder 8)
    - Art Properties Inc. financial statements and related correspondence, 1970-1971; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-03, Folder 9-10)
    - Arthur Andersen and Co., 1969-1971 (Box 1986.IA.11-03, Folder 11)
    - Art Properties Inc. audit, 1967-1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-03, Folder 12)
    - Financial statements, 1960-1970; [3 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-03, Folder 13-15)
    - IRS employee identification number, 1968 (Box 1986.IA.11-03, Folder 16)
    - Taxes, 1960-1971; [1-2 of 6 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-03, Folder 17-18)
    - Taxes, 1960-1971; [3-6 of 6 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-04, Folder 1-4)
    - Stock, 1969-1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-04, Folder 5)
    - Stock schedule, 1966-1968 (Box 1986.IA.11-04, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence and documents re: stock, 1960-1971; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-04, Folder 7-8)
    - Insurance, 1960-1977; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-04, Folder 9-10)
    - Bank signatories and bank data, 1960-1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-04, Folder 11)
    - Manufacturers Hanover Trust, 1966-1967 (Box 1986.IA.11-04, Folder 12)
    - Art Properties Inc./Wilmington Trust Co. cancelled checks and receipts, 1960-1966; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-04, Folder 13-14)
    - Wilmington Trust Co., 1960-1971; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-04, Folder 15-16)
    - Capital account, undated, 1967-1970; [1-2 of 3 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-04, Folder 17-18)
    - Capital account, voided, 1967-1969; [3 of 3 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 1)
    - Income account, 1970-1971; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 2-3)
    - Invoices and related correspondence, 1960-1971; [6 files] (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 4-9)
    - Abbott and Gerson, Ltd. check receipts, 1966-1968 (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 10)
    - Norris Bramlett check receipts, 1961; 1969 (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 11)
    - Brealey, John M. check receipts, 1965-1967 (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 12)
    - Collector of Internal Revenue check receipts, 1960; 1964 (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 13)
    - The Corporation Trust Co. check receipts, 1961-1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 14)
    - The Corporate Press, Inc.check receipts, 1961-1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 15)
    - Getty Oil Company check receipts, 1960-1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 16)
    - Duveen Brothers, Inc. check receipts, 1961-1962 (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 17)
    - J. Paul Getty check receipts, 1961; 1969 (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 18)
    - Professor Julius Held check receipts, 1962 (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 19)
    - Johnson and Higgins, 1961-1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1960-1970 (Box 1986.IA.11-05, Folder 21)
  - Vital records and seals, 1960-1971; Subseries I.D.; 1 Linear Feet (1 box)
    The volumes in this subseries are arranged by topic and then chronologically. The entries in the stock ledger and the certificates in the stock books are in straight chronological order. The general vital records are in reverse chronological order within each volume. The embossing seals are housed in a small box within the larger box of bound volumes.
    Scope and Contents
    This accession comprises six bound volumes containing the vital records of J. Paul Getty's company, Art Properties Inc., and two embossing seals (metal instruments) used to imprint paper documents with the company's official seal. The records in this subseries are generally signed originals; duplicate copies of many of these records exist in Subseries I.A, I.B., and I.C. above.
    The three black clothbound volumes comprise one stock ledger and two books of blank and cancelled stock certificates. The three red clothbound volumes titled "Art Properties, Inc." primarily contain original, signed documents, including articles of incorporation; bylaws; annual stockholders' meeting minutes; board of directors' meeting minutes and associated documents; signed officers' oaths; officer election information; and information on works of art, such as packing and freight details, copies of bills of sale, and canceled checks. Volume III. also includes an inventory and valuation of the art objects in the Great Hall at Sutton Place (Getty's British residence); a schedule and valuation of the art objects held by Art Properties Inc. at the time of its liquidation; and other documentation related to the official liquidation and dissolution of the company.
    - Volume I. Art Properties, Inc. vital records, 1960-1965 (Box 2009.IA.45-01)
    - Volume II. Art Properties, Inc. vital records, 1965-1969 (Box 2009.IA.45-01)
    - Volume III. Art Properties, Inc. vital records, 1970-1971 (Box 2009.IA.45-01)
    - Volume IV. Art Properties, Inc. stock and transfer ledger, 1960-1970 (Box 2009.IA.45-01)
    - Volume V. Art Properties, Inc. stock certificates, 1960-1969 (Box 2009.IA.45-01)
    - Volume VI. Art Properties, Inc. stock certificates, 1960-1970 (Box 2009.IA.45-01)
    - Corporate seal, circa 1960s (Box 2009.IA.45-01)
- Fine Arts Corporation, 1969-1982; Series II.; 3.6 Linear Feet (9 boxes)